Hello, and welcome to Lesson 4 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
您好，欢迎阅读Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第4课。
The topic for today’s lesson is the limit of a function, and it is today that we begin formally
今天的课程主题是函数的极限，从今天开始我们就正式学习微积分的概念。
the study of calculus in this course. The limits are an essential topic in any calculus course.
极限是任何微积分课程中必不可少的主题
Let’s begin with an overview of the topic.
让我们从主题概述开始。
Here are two simple plots. I’m going to plot x from −1 to 1. That is of course just a straight line,
这是两个简单的图。我打算将x从-1 绘制到1。这当然只是一条直线，
and then I’m going to plot x^2/x in the same limits, and I again get back what looks like
然后我将在相同的区域中绘制x ^ 2 / x，然后我再次得到类似的结果
essentially the same straight line. On the other hand, if we look at the function x^2/x,
基本相同的直线。让我们继续探究函数x ^ 2 / x，
then strictly speaking it’s not defined when x is 0 because you’re doing 0/0,
严格来说，当x为0 时函数没有定义，因为您正在计算0/0，
and that becomes clearer if we define a function g with that expression. g over here
如果我们用该表达式定义函数g，这将变得更加清楚。
is defined to be x^2/x, and if you try to find the value of g at 0, then you get back
g被定义为x ^ 2 / x，如果您尝试求出g在0处的值，则返回
the value indeterminate. The Quiet over only says that I would not like to see
一个Indeterminate（不确定）值。这里使用Quiet指令使得
any warnings that Wolfram Language would give us in this case.
Wolfram语言在此处不会显示错误警告。
Okay. The point is you have two very similar functions, but the second one has a slight issue at 0.
好的。现在您有两个非常相似的函数，但第二个函数在0处有一个小问题。
Now even though it is not defined at 0, you still would like to know what the behavior
现在，即使函数在0处没有定义，您仍然想知道它在该点附近区域的行为。
of the function is near this point, and that’s what limits are all about. They are about tracking
这就是极限。
the behavior of a function near a point. The mathematical way of doing this is called a limit.
我们要研究的就是函数在某点的邻域内的行为。做到这一点的数学方法就称为极限
Here’s an example to show the notion of a limit. Let’s take f[x] = x^2 − x + 2.
这是显示极限概念的示例。让我们取f [ x ] = x ^ 2 − x + 2。
Again, you want to find the behavior of this function as x approaches a certain value.
同样，您希望得知x接近某个值时此函数的行为。
Let’s say you want to focus on the value x = 1 and you make a table over here.
假设您要关注x = 1 的值，然后在此处制作表格。
Don’t worry too much about how to make the table; that’s not too important for us.
不用太担心如何在Woflram语言中创建表格；这对我们来说不太重要。
As you take values close to 1, you begin from 0 and go up to 1—very close to 1, but not 1 itself—
当您采用接近1的值时，变量值将从0开始上升至1（非常接近1，但本身不是1）
you see the values get close to 2. Just same thing happens from the right, that the value is
您会看到函数值接近2。从2的右边开始发生趋近也会发生同样的事情
very close to 2 when you are close to 1. It appears that this function gets closer and closer to 2
变量值趋近于1时，函数值趋近于2
as the values of x grow closer and closer to 1 from both the sides. One would then say that
总之，变量值x从两侧趋近于1时，函数值趋近于2
the limit of this function when x approaches 1 is 2. Limits are just
x接近1 时此函我们就称当x趋近于1时函数的极限是2。
a way of showing the behavior of a function near a point, but not necessarily at that point.
极限就是一种描述函数在某个点附近但不一定就在这个点上的行为的方式。
Okay. Some examples. Let’s begin with a function which is a trigonometric function divided by
好的。让我们来看一些例子。我们来看一个三角函数除以
a simple polynomial. It’s a trigonometric rational function, and you want to find
一个简单的多项式。这是一个三角有理函数，您想找到
the limit of this function as x approaches 0. If you look over here at the table, it’s clear that
当x趋近于0时，此函数的极限。如果您在此处查看值表，很明显
as you approach 0 from either side, the values approach 1. In fact if you plot the function,
当您从任一方向逼近0时，值都接近1。实际上，如果绘制函数，
you get the same kind of guess that the value of the limit seems to be 1. The table says 1,
您会得到相同的猜测，即该限制的值似乎为1。
the plot says 1, but in practice it’s best to use the Limit function in Wolfram Language,
无论是函数值表还是图像都告诉你极限是1，但实际上我们最好还是使用Wolfram语言中的Limit函数，
which tells you the limit is actually 1. Tables are good, plots are better, but Limit is the best.
结果确实是1。从值表可以看出极限，画图效果更好，但是使用Wolfram语言的Limit函数是最好的。
Limit will always tell you exactly what the limit of a function is at a point.
Limit函数将始终准确地告诉您某个函数的极限点。
The whole theme of our discussion will be try to move towards using Limit whenever you can.
我们整个讨论的主题将是尝试尽可能地使用Limit。
As my second example, let’s take a rational function. That’s a rational function.
作为第二个示例，让我们考虑一个有理函数。这是一个有理函数，
It’s a polynomial divided by a polynomial. Now notice that when x is plus or minus 1,
它是一个多项式除以多项式。现在请注意，当x为正负1时，
there’s a problem with the denominator becoming 0. Let’s say you want to talk about
分母变为0。我们来讨论
the behavior near −1. Near −1, it looks like the values are very close to −0.5.
变量在-1附近的函数行为。在-1附近，看起来值非常接近-0.5。
Now let’s plot the function, and it does look like when you are close to −1,
现在让我们来绘制函数，它看起来就像是当您接近-1时，
the values are close to −0.5. It looks like the function approaches −1/2 as an exact number
该值接近-0.5。
as x approaches −1. You can confirm that with Limit and get back that value as the actual limit.
您可以使用Limit函数验证这一点，得到严格的极限值
Okay. As my next example, let’s consider this piecewise function g[x].
好的。作为我的下一个示例，让我们考虑这个分段函数g [ x ]。
Now the piecewise part over here is all simple. It’s just −0.75 at x = −1,
现在，这里的分段部分非常简单。当x = -1时函数值为-0.75 ，
and it’s the same rational function as before everywhere else. Now if you make a table of values,
在别处它就和普通的有理函数一样。现在，如果您创建一个值表，
it’s clear that as long as you stay away from −1, then there’s no problem at all
显然，只要我们不讨论-1处的情况，就根本没有问题
and the values approach −0.5 as before. Here’s a plot which shows that there’s a problem
值和以前一样接近-0.5。这是函数图形，表明在-1处
at just a single point, −1, but everywhere else, things are just the same as before.
有一个单独的游离点，但在其他任何地方，情况都与以前相同。
In fact, the limit does seem to be −0.5. Let’s confirm that over here, and you do get back −0.5
实际上，该极限似乎确实是-0.5。让我们在这里确认一下，这个分段函数的
for this piecewise function limit.
极限值确实是0.5
Now, let’s go on to a slightly more complicated example; namely, an algebraic function.
现在，让我们继续一个稍微复杂的例子。即代数函数。
Here’s an algebraic function. It’s got a square root in it and the denominator x^2, so when x is 0,
这是一个代数函数。它的平方根和分母x ^ 2，所以当x为0时，
that’s a problem. But fortunately everything is removable in the sense that
会出现问题。但幸运的是，从某种意义上说，这些都是可去的
there really is no problem at 0. In fact, if we make a table of values, you see that
在0处实际上不会有问题。实际上，如果我们创建一个值表，您会看到
when you are very close to 0, the value is very close to 0.25. You plot the function,
当您非常接近0时，该值非常接近0.25。您绘制函数，
and you see that the value at 0 does seem to approach 0.25. You can confirm the answer with Limit,
您会发现0处的值确实接近0.25。您可以使用Limit函数来确认答案，
and you get back the value 0.25 as an exact number, 1/4.
然后您将得到精确数字1/4。
Okay. Let’s go on now to a slightly more tricky function. Here is a trigonometric function.
好的。现在让我们继续一个稍微棘手的函数。这是一个三角函数。
Now if we make a table of values over here, what you see is that the values all seem to be 1 mostly.
现在，如果我们在此处制作一个值表，您将看到的是，这些值似乎大多都是1。
It looks like there is a problem because the limit seems to be 1. Intuition tells you that
但是这里似乎有问题，因为极限看上去是1。直觉告诉您
this might be more complicated, so let’s plot. Then you do that. You see it is much more wiggly.
这可能会更复杂，所以让我们作图。您会发现它在不断震荡。
It’s much more complicated. What you need to take away from this is that
它非常复杂。这告诉我们
tables are useful, but they are not terribly reliable. The plot says that this limit
值表是有用的，但并不是十分可靠。函数的图像告诉我们
probably does not exist, but in fact you can confirm the answer with Limit, and check that
极限可能不存在，但实际上您可以使用Limit确认答案，
the answer is actually indeterminate. Indeterminate says that this limit does not exist.
给出的结果是极限是不确定的。不确定表示此极限不存在。
Okay. Let’s move on now to a slightly more complicated function, and hopefully you realize by now
好的。现在让我们继续一个稍微复杂的函数，希望您现在已经意识到
that we do need some different ways of finding limits. But just for now,
我们确实需要一些不同的方法来寻找极限。但是就目前而言
let’s take the same approach and make a table of values over here.
让我们采用相同的方法，并在此处制作一个值表。
When you make a table of values and you are close to 0, you see the values
当您创建一个值表并且接近0时，您会看到这些值
seem to approach 0.015 on either side. As an exact number, you would expect
似乎两边都接近0.015。用精确数字来表达，就是
the limit to be around 3/200. You plot the function. The limit does look like 0.015 at 0.
极限在3/200左右。您绘制函数。极限确实在0处看起来像0.015。
You can confirm the answer with Limit and get back the correct result, which is 3/200.
您可以使用Limit确认答案，然后返回正确的结果，即3/200。
That’s the value of the limit function. It will tell you exactly what the limit is at a point.
那就是极限函数的值。它会告诉您确切的极限值。
Okay. Having talked about limits, it’s convenient sometimes to talk about one-sided limits.
好的。讨论了极限之后，有时讨论从单边趋近的极限会很方便。
Here’s an example where you have a piecewise function, and if you plot it, you see that
这是一个具有分段函数的示例，如果绘制它，您会看到
when you approach the point 0 from the left, the answer is −1. When you approach it from the right,
当您从左侧接近点0时，极限是-1。当您从右侧接近时，
the limit seems to be 1. The question is how do you check that with the Limit function?
限制似乎是1。问题是如何使用Limit函数进行检查？
Well, we have an option called Direction, so when you say Direction→“FromBelow”,
好吧，Limit函数有一个称为Direction的选项，所以当您设定Direction→“ FromBelow”时，
you’re going from the left; when it’s Direction→“FromAbove”, you’re going from the right.
你从左边趋近；当它是Direction→“FromAbove”时，极限从右边趋近。
When you do that, you see that you get back the values −1 and 1 respectively. Of course because
这样做时，您会看到分别返回值-1和1。
you don’t have the same behavior on the left and right, you get back indeterminate
由于分别从作用两边趋近的话，函数表现出不同的行为，
as the answer for the limit. One-sided limits are really quite useful because they let you
因此极限的答案是不确定。单限制非常有用，因为它们可以让您
analyze more and more complicated functions.
分析越来越复杂的函数。
Here is a piecewise function. It’s got several pieces. Notice that when you plot the function,
这是一个分段函数。它分为几块。请注意，在绘制函数时，
then there are three values of interest to us: there’s 1, there’s 4 and there’s 6.
那么我们感兴趣的是三个变量值：1，4，6。
Now 4 is not a problem at all; it’s nice over there. At 1, it’s almost okay, except that
在4处没有问题。在1处，这几乎没问题，
you have a slight piece outside of the point over here given by this piecewise component.
分段函数给定了在这些（值）之外还有一点。
At 6, you have a slightly more difficult problem because you actually have a jump.
在6处，您会遇到一个稍微困难的问题，因为这里实际上有一个跳跃。
It would look like when you approach 1, the value must be 3 for the limit. That’s 3 over here.
接近1时，该值明显为3。
When you approach 4, the answer must be 6. That looks clear as well. Now when you approach 6 itself,
当您接近4时，答案明显是6。这看起来也很清楚。现在，当您接近6时，
the limit does not seem to exist, and you can confirm this by using the Limit function.
该极限似乎不存在，您可以使用Limit函数进行确认。
Now this strange thing over here is what we call a Map function, which actually lets you find
这个稍显奇怪的记号这是我们的Map函数，它实际上使您只用一条指令
the values of the limits at different points in one stroke. You can confirm that at 6 you actually have
找到不同点的函数值。您可以确认在6处，
separate limits on the right and left by doing the direction computation,
确实有分离的左右极限
and you get back different answers, so surely the limit does not exist at x = 6.
并且您得到不同的答案，因此肯定在x = 6时不存在极限。
Okay. Now we need to turn in a slightly different direction and talk about infinite limits.
好的。现在我们需要转向一个略有不同的方向，并讨论无限的极限。
Here’s an example where you have a rational function, and what you want to do is to use
这是一个示例，其中您有一个有理函数，而您想要做的就是使用
a table of values that’s given to you to try and guess what the limit might be at the point x = −1.
一张给出的值表，您可以尝试猜测x = -1 处的极限。
Here’s the table, and what you see is that when they approach −1 on the left or right,
这是表格，您会看到，当它们在左侧或右侧接近-1时，
the values seem to blow up—they become infinite—but they become negatively infinite
值似乎爆炸了—它们变为无限—而这里变为负无限
on one side and positively infinite on this side. You can confirm that with the Limit function.
您可以使用Limit函数进行确认。
You see that the values become −∞ on one side and ∞ on the other,
您会看到极限值在一侧变为-∞，在另一侧变为∞，
and you can check that the limit does not exist, finally. Now we are talking about infinite limits,
最后，您可以检查该极限是否存在。现在我们在谈论无限的极限，
and that leads us to the concept of an asymptote. What’s an asymptote? It’s a point in the graph
这就引出了渐近线的概念。什么是渐近线？这是图中的一点
where things become infinite. Here’s an example. You’ve got 1/(x − 1)^2 as a function,
事物变得无限的地方。这是一个例子。您有1 /（x − 1）^ 2作为函数，
and whether you approach it at 1 from the left or right, the value becomes infinitely large
并且无论您是从左侧还是右侧以1接近它，该值都会变得正无限大
in a positive sense, and you can confirm that with a plot to check
。你可以通过画图来验证这一点。
the limit is actually going to be ∞ on either side. Well, if it’s infinite on either side, it is ∞,
极限实际上在任一侧都是∞。好吧，如果两边都是无限的，则为∞，
so Limit says yes, the limit is ∞ at 1. That’s what we call a vertical asymptote.
所以Limit告诉我们，极限在1处是∞。这就是我们所说的垂直渐近线。
It’s a kind of vertical line that shows you that the function will become infinite
这是一条垂直线，向您显示该函数在两边都将变为无限
on both sides, in this case.
But it can also have slightly different behavior. Here’s f[x] = 1/x, and if you plot it between −1 and 1,
但是它的行为也可能略有不同。这是f [ x ] = 1 / x，如果将其绘制在-1和1之间，
then at 0 you have a different behavior on the left and the right—so on the right, it approaches ∞;
那么在0处，它的左右行为就不同了-因此在右边，它接近∞；
on the left, it approaches −∞, and you can confirm that with Limit. You see the limit does not exist,
在左边，它接近-∞，您可以用Limit确认。您会发现该极限不存在，
and what you have is a vertical asymptote of a slightly different kind.
而您所拥有的是一种稍有不同的垂直渐近线。
Okay. The question is how do you find asymptotes in general? Well, that’s really a hard problem,
好的。问题是，您一般如何找到渐近线？好吧，这确实是一个难题。
but let’s say if I give you a cotangent function and I said find the asymptotes between −2π and 2π,
但是，如果我给你一个余切函数，并且说找到−2π和2π之间的渐近线，
what you could do is make a plot of the function. The plot seems to say that there are
您可以做的是对该函数作图。图像似乎说有
problems at 0—you can see over here—and then at π and then at 2π, et cetera. Let’s look at 0.
0处的问题-您可以在此处查看-然后π处，然后是2π处，诸如这样。让我们看一下0处。
You see that the function values are −∞ and ∞ from the two sides, so you certainly have
您会看到函数值从两侧趋近分别为-∞和∞，因此您当然拥有
a vertical asymptote at 0, and just the same thing happens at all the other multiples of π.
在0处的垂直渐近线，并且在π的所有其他倍数处发生相同的事情。
You can see that the limit does not exist at any of those points. Given a function,
您可以看到该极限在这些时刻的任意一者都不存在。给定一个函数
you could try to plot it and then use Limit to figure out where the asymptotes might be.
您可以尝试将其绘制出来，然后使用Limit找出渐近线的位置。
Okay. Finally I have an example in which you actually do need to use tables.
好的。最后，我有一个示例，其中您实际上确实需要使用值表。
Here is an example in which you have two variables. You have got an h and an x.
这是一个有两个变量的示例。您有一个h和一个x。
Now the problem is that because x is not known to you, you cannot graph the function,
现在的问题是，因为您不知道x，所以无法绘制函数的图形，
so graphing will get you nowhere in this case. But what you could do is make a table of values,
因此在这种情况下，绘图将无济于事。但是您可以做的是制作一张值表，
and then what you see is—well, roughly speaking—if you expand it out, you get x^2 + 2xh + h^2 − x^2.
然后，如果你展开它，能得到x ^ 2 + 2 xh + h ^ 2- − x ^ 2。
If you do a bit of algebra, it will be clear to you that what is going to get left over is just 2x.
如果您做一点代数，您会很清楚，剩下的就是2 x。
Right. The point over here is the limit over here is just going to be 2x.
对。此处的点是此处的极限将仅为2 x。
Okay. We’ve seen now that tables are quite useful in some cases,
好的。现在我们已经看到值表在某些情况下非常有用，
but in general, you should try and avoid them.
但总的来说，您应该尽量避免使用它们。
That brings me to the end of today’s lesson. What you’ve learned is that the limits are a good way of
这使我到今天课程的结尾。您了解到，
figuring out what happens as a function approaches a certain value of x.
极限是弄清楚函数接近某个x值的行为的好方法。
Now the function doesn’t even need to be defined at the point at which you want to find the limit,
现在，您甚至不需要在要查找极限的位置定义函数，
but as long as the right-hand limit and the left-hand limit both exist, you are fine.
但只要右边和左边都存在，就可以了。
For a limit to exist, you must have the right-hand limit and the left-hand limit to be equal.
极限存在的条件是，您必须使右边的限制和左边的极限相等。
They could both be infinite, but they must both be equal. As you saw in the last example,
它们可能都是无限的，但必须都相等。如上例所示，
tables are really useful in some cases, but in general, you want to avoid using them,
值表在某些情况下确实很有用，但总的来说，您要避免使用它们，
and you really want to use the Limit function. In the next lesson, we’ll talk the laws of limits,
我们鼓励多采用Limit函数。在下一课中，我们将讨论极限定律，
which actually let you do limit computations very efficiently without using tables.
实际上，您无需使用值表即可非常有效地计算极限。
But before we do that, I recommend that you go over today’s lesson and carefully master all the details
但是在我们这样做之前，我建议您仔细阅读今天的课程，并仔细掌握所有细节
from the notebook, look at the exercises and make sure you understand
从笔记本上，看一下练习并确保您了解极限的概念。
the notion of a limit really well before we actually start computing them at a really fast pace.
下节课我们将能快速地计算极限。
That’s all I have to say for today’s lesson on the limit of a function. I hope you enjoyed it.
对于今天的函数限制，这就是今天的内容。
I hope you really benefit from this first introduction to calculus with limits
希望您能从这节课对极限的介绍中有所收获。